<changes>
    <!--
        Copyright 2024 Tamas Bolner

        Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
        you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
        You may obtain a copy of the License at

            http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

        Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
        distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
        WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
        See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
        limitations under the License.
    -->

    <add
        documentID="phi1348.abo011"
        language="english"
        after="chapter=48"
        key="chapter=49"
        before="chapter=50"
    >
    (Thomson has omitted this chapter. The following is a translation by ChatGPT.)


    </add>

    <add
        documentID="phi0631.phi001"
        language="english"
        after="chapter=34"
        key="chapter=35"
        before="chapter=36"
    >
    (Missing chapter. The following is a translation by ChatGPT.)
    Your outstanding loyalty, proven by experience, and valued by me in my great dangers, gives me
    confidence in my recommendation. For this reason, I have not decided to prepare a defense in
    the new plan; I have resolved to propose my satisfaction based on a clear conscience of no
    guilt, which, by Hercules, you may truly know. Provoked by injuries and insults, because I was
    deprived of the rewards of my labor and industry, and did not obtain the position of dignity, I
    undertook the public cause of the unfortunate, according to my custom, not because I could not
    pay off my debts from my possessions, and the generosity of Orestilla would settle them from
    her and her daughter's resources, but because I saw that unworthy men were being honored and I
    felt myself estranged by false suspicion. For this reason, I pursued with sufficient integrity,
    given my circumstances, the hope of preserving the remaining dignity. While I wanted to write
    more, it was announced that violence was being prepared against me. Now, I entrust Orestilla to
    your loyalty and commend her to your protection; I ask that you defend her from injury through
    your children! Farewell!
    </add>

    <add
        documentID="phi0631.phi001"
        language="english"
        after="chapter=56"
        key="chapter=57"
        before="chapter=58"
    >
    (Missing chapter. The following is a translation by ChatGPT.)
    But after the messenger reached the camp with news that the conspiracy in Rome had been uncovered,
    and that punishment had been inflicted on Lentulus, Cethegus, and the others whom I mentioned
    before, most of those who had been lured to war by the hope of plunder or the desire for
    revolution dispersed; the rest, Catiline led through the rough mountains by forced marches into
    the territory of Pistoria, with the plan to escape secretly through the byways into Transalpine
    Gaul. However, Quintus Metellus Celer was stationed with three legions in the Picene territory,
    suspecting the same plans of Catiline that we mentioned earlier due to the difficulties of the
    situation. Therefore, when he learned of Catiline's route from deserters, he quickly moved his
    camp and settled at the very foot of the mountains, where Catiline's descent into Gaul would have
    been in haste. However, Antonius was not far off either, since he was following closely with a
    large army, moving more easily in the more level areas. But when Catiline saw that he was hemmed
    in by the mountains and the enemy forces, with adverse news from the city, and no hope of either
    flight or protection, he decided that the best course of action in such circumstances was to try
    the fortune of battle, and so he resolved to engage with Antonius as soon as possible. Therefore,
    after calling an assembly, he delivered a speech of this kind:
    </add>
</changes>
